Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Carlow
    His early pleadings for the rights of America; what Ireland did for America deserves very warm returns in National connection and friendship. His fears for America caused by the talk of disbanding the army without the troops having received their arrears. Has left Dublin and is enjoying the diversion of shooting. Concerning the reforms they hope to make in their Parliament. Injury to Ireland by the changes in the British Ministry; characters of the Viceroys. Lack of able and worthy men in Dublin to put forward as candidates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Introducing the Comtesse de Fries, whose husband is a banker in Vienna, one of the richest and most respectable men in Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 Januray 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Valazé, Charles Eléonor Dufriche de
    Asks for an audience that he may present Franklin with a copy of a work entitled "Lois Pénales," which he has dedicated to the brother of the King [Comte de Provence]; desires Franklin to forward a copy to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 15; Thomson, Charles. Annapolis
    Treaty of Peace ratified by Congress. Account of various inquiries he has made at Franklin's request. Measures proposed for the payment of debts contracted during the war. Praise of Col. [David Salisbury] Franks.
    Printed, in part. in Works (Sparks, X, 56; Bigelow, VIII, 430).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Treuttel, -----. Strasbourg
    Desires to be the first to present Franklin with a copy of the American Almanac, undertaken at Berlin; sends it by M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval]; is open to any order for it which Franklin may send him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; D'assarts, Dupin. Paris
    Account of his miserable situation with no work and a wife and four children to support; begs Franklin for a small loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Grosett, Charles. Brunswick
    Laying before Franklin his plan for the establishment in America of a superfine cloth, cashmere and frieze manufactory; one hundred Protestant emigrants, qualified for the different parts of the business, are willing to embark with him; desires to know whether such an establishment would be welcome and what encouragement it would receive.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Toustain, Charles-Gaspard de Toustain-Richebourg, vicomte de. Paris
    As a member and Corresponding Secretary of the Société Partriotique-Bretoune, is deputed to inform Franklin of the highly flattering testimonials rendered to his and Gen. Washington's qualities at their last meeting; M. le Comte de Sérent was the orator of the occasion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Tahon, J. Armentières
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to his brother in Boston; his letter thus far have always failed to reach him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 17; L.S. 3p.; Charrené, Jn. London
    Delivered the letter to Mr. [John] Sargent. Begs Franklin's interest with M. [Charles Eugène Gabriel de la Croix, Marquis] de Casrtries to obtain the defrayal of his personal expenses during his three years' service in England; is heavily in debt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Fleury, ----- de
    Begs that the enclosed letters may be forwarded to America by the first opportunity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 18; L. 3p.; Eckhardt, Anthony George. Utrecht
    Concerning M. Montgolfier's discovery and the results of certain experiments made by them which they would be only too glad to communicate to the above distinguished inventor ;explains his scheme, to be employed in voyages of discovery, of attaching the balloon by a cord to the vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Sambres, Brouttin Mollien de
    Desires to know if a memoir of Benjamin Morel of Dunkirk, which she sent him, arrived safely and what hopes she may give her relative.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Denis, Mme and daughter
    Recalling themselves to his remembrance and requesting an audience with him at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 [January?] 18; Engraved N. in 3d P.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 Januray 19; A.L.S. 6p.; Heyman, Herman. Bremen
    Concerning establishing a glass factory in Maryland; their intention to send their friend, Mr. Amelong, to Baltimore in the spring, together with eighty families all experienced in the business; begs for letters of introduction and recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Chase, Samuel. London
    Pleasure at his recovery. Loss of a ship in which he [Chase] was considerably interested; question of Mr.[John] Jay's preparing and presenting a memorial on the subject; begs Franklin's influence with the Marquis de Castries and de la Fayette. Small prospect of obtaining the Bank [of England] stock. Expects to return to Maryland in February or March.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Feriet, -----, baron de
    Describing a house and garden at Versailles which he thinks would suit Franklin; its distance from the Chateau; suggests Franklin's grandson coming to look at it;offers also to show him a collection of sedanchairs, from which he can select one for Franklin. Account of an harmonica sent to the Duchesse de Villeroy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Steps he has taken to produce the information about the value of the two ships. Thanks him for his intended kindness in respect to the Consulship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Gombert, ------ de
    Offering Franklin a valuable discovery he has made; a sure preventative against all toothache; realizes that this secret, if revealed, will do great injury to the dentists, but his object is to be useful to humanity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Bird, Samuel. Andelys
    As he has the honor of Franklin's protection for the establishment of a woolen manufactory in the United States, gives him a detailed account of his business abilities; prefers holding a salaried position under any gentleman who is willing to carry out this project.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Lagarde, -----. Paris
    Account of his medical training and experience; offers his services to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Longchamps, -----
    Concerning a manuscript presented to his son as part-payment for instructing the child of the author; owing to his financial looses, he is anxious to dispose of the ms.; high opinion of its excellence expressed by several book-sellers; offers to sell it to Franklin; thinks it might prove useful to instruct the young Anglo-American nobility.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Paris
    Transmitting Franklin a piece written in America against the Cincinnati, and a newspaper containing the institutions of that Society; when Franklin writes on this subject to M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval], begs him to present his respectful compliants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Pous-Ludon, Hédoin de
    Begging Franklin to use his influence to obtain for him the position of Agent for Wines, now at the disposal of Maréchal de Sainey; asks this favor on the strength of their being brother Masons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; La Brossière, Mallet de
    Account of his thirteen years of service as a surgeon in the French army; has nothing to show for it expect his impaired health; offers his services to America; desires to be put in charge of a military hospital there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    Introducing to Franklin his friend, [Robert John] Thomton, a student of medicine, who expects to study French and surgery in Paris. His purpose to make an elegant edition of Dr. [John] Fothergill's life, in which will appear anecdotes and portraits of Franklin and others of Dr. Fothergill's friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of Sweden
    Regrets being unable to accept his invitation but will call on him to exchage notifications.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Longchamps, -----
    Hopes that the manuscript (XXXI, 46) sent to Franklin will meet with his approbation; if he has no use for it, begs he will at least render him some assistance in his present unfortunate situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan. Nantes
    Concerning the sentence pronounced against him by the Court of Admiralty, relative to the insurance of the ship "Nancy"; reasons why he has ordered an appeal; is nevertheless obliged to pay the full premium at once; begs Franklin's protection in this affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 January 31; A.L.S. 3p.; David Gallwey and Co. Nantes
    Wrote Franklin on the 22d inst. relative to the insurance on the American ship "Nancy"; conditions of the policy; in spite of proofs in their possession, the sentence was aginst them; have entered an appeal but they will be obliged to pay the money if Franklin does not interfere and obtain a quick decision from the Minister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Strahan, William. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's and the Bache family's kindness to his young kinswoman. Urging him to spend the rest of his days in England. Recommending the bearer, Dr. Ross, who has served as physician to the English army in the East, but who now desires to pursue his profession in America; Franklin's recommendation would be of great service to him. The present political confusion.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, X, 65; Bigelow, VIII, 446).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Announcing his acquittal and discharge; has now the right to pursue those who were the cause of his disgrace; desires the publication of his trail in order that his countrymen may be convinced of his innocence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Roberdeau, Daniel. London
    Recommending to Franklin's attention, Mr. Vanderhorst and his daughter who go to Paris for a short stay; on their return, begs that they may be entrusted with the money for the bill of exchange sent to Franklin. Intends on his return to America, to establish a refinery in addition to his distillery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
    Announcing the acquittal and discharge of [John] Schaffer; uses every argument to persuade him that Schaffer merited his esteem; desires Franklin's help to enable his client to publish an account of his trial, as his compatriots may be interested in his triumphant vindication; for this purpose, the celebrated [John] Paul Jones has promised to subscribe; Schaffer's intention to quit France as soon as his affairs are arranged; believes his experience will teach him an important lesson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
    Has just left the Magistrate who has received no answer from him relative to the verification of his signature; implores him to hasten his reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 3; L.S. 1p.; Waldner, ---- countess de
    Regrets leaving Passy without seeing Franklin. Asks for a little advice concerning an island, by name Brid, which she hears the Americans desire to repeople; a young man, a relative of one of her waiting women, desires to go there; begs Franklin to grant the young man his protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Begs for information as to what passes between the Duke of Dorset and the Dutch Ministers on the subject of converting the preliminary agreement into a definitive treaty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Failly, Chevalier de
    Detailed account of his services in America, the battles he fought and the honors he received; begs Franklin to procure his admission to that noble association [the Society of the Cincinnati].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Mifflin, Thomas. Annapolis
    Recommending to Franklin's notice Lieut-Col. [Josiah] Harmar, a very deserving officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis
    The stove is finished according to Franklin's plan; begs him to visit the stove-maker and ascertain if there are any faults to be corrected; his brother [Louis Claude Cadet-Gassicourt] desires that Franklin will dine with him on that day; will call for him at Passy, if he will name the day and hour.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Longchamps, -----
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter which announces the miscarriage of the manuscript; will take his advice concerning its disposal; as Franklin does not wish to buy it, begs him for a small loan of five louis d'or to enable him to meet a business obligation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Begs for a certificate of good character in order to secure his release from prison.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbançon, comte de
    [William] Bartram's letter; reminds Franklin of his promise to make use of him to procure certain natural specimens, as yet unknown in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
    Concerning a bill of sixty dollars sent to Franklin to verify the signature, hopes he will do this and deliver the bill only to [J.] Schaffer himself; this money is his sole resource; without it, he cannot publish an account of his trial and thereby reinstate himself in his countrymen's good opinion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 10; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Recommending to Franklin's acquaintance his good friend, Abbè [J.] Nckrep, President of the Oriental College at Vienna, a very good scholar and philosopher; his reasons for deciding to give up their plan of constructing a balloon. Sorry to hear that Franklin has a stone in the bladder; remedies for this disease; no cure as yet discovered; gives him some medical advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 10; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gourdon, ---- de
    He and his wife accept with pleasure Franklin's kind invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Valazé, Charles Eléonor Dufriche de
    Sends him a copy of his work; if he reads and approves it, he will not refuse to receive the copy destined for Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 10.; A.L.S. 2p.; Longchamps fils, -----
    Reasons why his father sent the manuscript to Franklin; has offered it to one of the Editiors of the Journal Militaire who gave him hopes of accepting it; the publication however will be too late to help them in their present difficulties; applies for a small loan to tide them over this critical period.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 11; A.L.S. 2p.; L'Auréole, ----- de
    Understands that Franklin employs workmen in his printing-house in Philadelphia; offers his services; if this is impossible, desires to teach Latin and other branches; can furnish excellent references.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. His correspondent misinformed; does not employ persons in America in that business; believes it would be difficult for one who is a stranger to the language to find such employment there.
    - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Tourton, --------
      Wishes to see him on an important matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 11.; N. in 3d P. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    Hindered by a previous engagement from accepting Franklin's kind invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Cramer, Catherine de Wesselow. Genève
    Her satisfaction in Franklin's account of his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache]; sure that Franklin will be content with his disposition and good sense; is not so certain about his studies; his stay with his grandfather will doubtless bring out all his latent talents.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Letter from the Stadtholder to the states of Zealand, which has added fuel to the fire. Anxious for news of what is passing in Paris between the English and Dutch Ministers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis
    Messrs. Quinquet and Lange, inventors of the lamp, are very anxious to submit it to Franklin's opinion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 15; A.L.S. 3p.; St. Olympe, -----, chevalier de
    Concerning the discovery by M. de Lestrades, King's physician at Martinique, of a remedy for the stone; nothing is lacking to the doctor's glory except the honor of prolonging Franklin's days; urges him to try this remedy; hopes on his return to Paris to hear that it has proved successful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784] February 15; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Reasons why she has not written; constantly thinking of and missing him.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 169.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 15.; A.L.S. 4p.; Perrin, D. Varennes
    Reminding Franklin of the important services he rendered him during his unfortunate stay in Montreal, and the promise made him of some recompense; since then has been ruined by a law-suit and is now left without means and with a family dependent on him; begs Franklin to make up a subscription among his friends and send it to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 16; A.L.S. 2p.; [Roncelle?], ------
    Announcing the death of his father-in-law, M. Macquer; as soon as he is able, will inform Franklin of his last wishes in favor of one of his relations; reminds Franklin of their first meeting and of their conversation on the subject, which interested M. Macquer intensely.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 17; L.S. 1p.; Barclay, Thomas. London
    Mr. [William] Hodgson's search for precedents relative to the capture of vessels situated like the "Nancy"; a trial to determine that point expected to come off very soon; promise of mr. Hodgson to send particulars of the decision. Is detained on matters connected with the public accounts. Likelihood of Mr. [Robert] Morris's bills on the negotiators of the loan in Holland being paid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784?] February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Acknowledging the papers on balloons. Prevented by the cold weather from waiting on Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Forwarded the letter by the packet from New York and charged the bill for postage to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Necessary to have Franklin's evidence in Court concerning a bill of Messrs. Bache and Shee; thinks a written statement would be received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 21; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Massieu, Madame de
    Sorry, to have missed him when she called. Desires to know what M. de Morel may expect from Franklin's kindness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; La Porte, ----- de
    Writes on behalf of La Baronne de Bissy, who has been left with six children to educate; begs Franklin's influence to place one of them in the merchant marine; the father's services in the navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Weinlandt, Johann Caspar. Römhild near Coburg, Franconia
    Concerning the establishment of a cut-glass and mirror factory in America, and, if material be here, to establish a blue-color (Woad) factory. Conditions of establishment. A student of theology is willing to join the emigrants and serve as preacher.
    (In German, accompanied by a French translation.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Fonténai, Abbé de
    At the request of a distinguished officer who served in America, writes to beg Franklin for the title and address of General Washington and of the President of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 25; L.S. 1p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Deputed by the Royal Society of Medicine to send Franklin the enclosed tickets for the next public meeting; expects to read enlogies on William Hunter and [Antoine Nunez Ribeiro] Sanchez; Franklin's presence would be a great encouragement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, John. London
    Informed by Mr. Vanderhorst of Franklin's anxiety concerning the health of his friend Dr. [Samuel] Cooper of Boston; greatly grieved at having to announce his death.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Murinais, comte de
    Writes on behalf of La Princesse Sapicha who desires to know if a Polish gentleman, by name [Thaddeus] Kosciusko, is still alive; begs for a line.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1784 February 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Miollis, Sextus Alexandre François, Aix-en-Provence
    Requesting to be made a member of the Society of Cincinnatus; this would be the most acceptable compensation they could offer him for the wound he received at the siege of Yorktown.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Legouvé, -----
    Encouraged to invite him to a ball at his mother's house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Roberdeau, Daniel. Gravesend
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 13th and his kind attention to Mr. Vanderhorst and his daughter; especially grateful for the assistance rendered his son relative to the art of refining sugar; desires to know if his son could be introduced as a workman at Bercy where he could hear more of the "new principles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Ginet and Meirieu. Paris
    Enclosing a bill of exchange for Franklin's acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 26; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseau, John. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's precious present; greatly pleased with the valuable contents of the book; thinks it proves not only the wisdom of the American legislators but the manliness of the whole country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Recalls himself to Franklin's memory by sending him a memoir on an important matter. The printer, de Monville, will give him the copies which he decided to send to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Mazue, -----. Marseilles
    Desires to lay before him a plan for the cultivation of the vine in America; question of the proper land and climate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Trembinski, Comte Biberstein. Havre in Normandy
    Through the kindness of the Due de la Rochefoucauld, received Franklin's letter of introduction to Congress; his ardent desire to see America; fears that the state of his health may prevent his making the voyage; prophesies a great future for the new republic.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 February 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John